Flies. Chapter 11, Castle Rock. In the short chill of dawn, the four boys
gathered round the black smudge where the fire had been, while Ralph knelt and
blew. Gray feathery ashes scured hither and thither at his breath, but no spark
shown among them. The twins watched anxiously, and Piggy sat expressionless
behind the luminous wall of his myopia. Ralph continued to blow till his
ears were singing with the effort, but then the first breeze of dawn took the
job off his hands and blinded him with ashes.
He squatted back, swore, and rubbed water out of his eyes. No use. Eric
looked down at him through a mask of dried blood. Piggy peered in the general
direction of Ralph. Of course, it's no use, Ralph. Now we got no fire. Ralph
brought his face within a couple of feet of piggies. Can you see me a bit? Ralph
allowed the swollen flap of his cheek to close his eye again. They've got our
fire. Rage shrilled his voice. They stole it. That's them, said Piggy. They
blinded me. See, that's Jack Meridu. You call an assembly, Ralph. We got to
decide what to do. An assembly for only us. It's all we got. Sam, let me hold on
to you. They went toward the platform.
Blow the conchk, said Piggy. Blow as loud as you can. The forests re-echoed,
and birds lifted, crying out of the treetops as on that first morning ages
ago. Both ways the beach was deserted.
Some little onins came from the shelters. Ralph sat down on the polished
trunk and the three others stood before him. He nodded and Sam and Eric sat down
on the right. Ralph pushed the conchk into Piggy's hands. He held the shining
thing carefully and blinked at Ralph. Go on then. I just take the conchk to say
this. I can't see no more and I got to get my glasses back. Awful things has
been done on this island. I voted for you for chief. He's the only one who
ever got anything done. So now you speak, Ralph, and tell us what. Or else.
Piggy broke off, sniveling. Ralph took back the con as he sat down. Just an
ordinary fire. You'd think we could do that, wouldn't you? Just a smoke signal
so we can be rescued. Are we savages or what? Only now there's no signal going
up. Ships may be passing. Do you remember how he went hunting and the
fire went out and a ship passed by? And they all think he's best as chief. Then
there was there was that's his fault, too. If it hadn't been for him, it would never have
happened. Now Piggy can't see. And they came stealing. Ralph's voice ran up at
night in darkness and stole our fire.
They stole it. We'd have given them fire if they'd asked, but they stole it. And
the signal's out, and we can't ever be rescued. Don't you see what I mean? We'd
have given them fire for themselves.
Only they stole it.
I He paused lamely as the curtain flickered in his brain. Piggy held out his hands for the
conchk. What you going to do, Ralph?
This is just talk without deciding. I want my glasses. I'm trying to think.
Supposing we go looking like we used to, washed and hairbrushed. After all, we
aren't savages really, and being rescued isn't a game. He opened the flap of his
cheek and looked at the twins. "We could smarten up a bit and then go. We ought
to take spears, said Sam. Even Piggy, because we may need them. You haven't
got the conchk. Piggy held up the shell.
You can take spears if you want, but I shant. What's the good? I'll have to be
led like a dog anyhow. Yes, laugh. Go on, laugh. There's them on this island,
as would laugh at anything. And what happened? What's grown-ups going to
think? Young Simon was murdered. And there was that other kid with had a mark
on his face. Who seen him since we first come here? Piggy, stop a minute. I got
the conchk. I'm going to that jack me and tell him I am. You'll get hurt. What
can he do more than he has? I'll tell him what's what. You let me carry the
conchk, Ralph. I'll show him the one thing he hasn't got. Piggy paused for a
moment and peered round at the dim figures. The shape of the old assembly
trotten in the grass. Listen to him. I'm going to him with this conchk in my
hands. I'm going to hold it out. Look, I'm going to say you're stronger than I
am and you haven't got asthma. You can see, I'm going to say, and with both
eyes. But I don't ask for my glasses back. Not as a favor. I don't ask you to
be a sport, I'll say. Not because you're strong, but because what's right's
right. Give me my glasses. I'm going to say you got to. Piggy ended, flushed and
trembling. He pushed the conchk quickly into Ralph's hands as though in a hurry
to be rid of it, and wiped the tears from his eyes. The green light was
gentle about them, and the conchk lay at Ralph's feet, fragile and white. A
single drop of water that had escaped Piggy's fingers now flashed on the delicate curve like a
star. At last Ralph sat up straight and drew back his hair. "All right, I mean
you can try if you like. We'll go with you." "He'll be painted," said Sam
timidly. "You know how he'll be. He won't think much of us. If he gets waxy,
we've had it." Ralph scowlled at Sam Dimly. He remembered something Simon had
said to him once by the rocks. Don't be silly, he said, and then he added
quickly. Let's go. He held out the conchk to Piggy, who flushed, this time
with pride. You must carry it. When we're ready, I'll carry it. Piggy sought
in his mind for words to convey his passionate willingness to carry the conchk against all
odds. I don't mind. I'll be glad, Ralph.
Only I'll have to be led. Ralph put the conchk back on the shining log. We
better eat and then get ready. They made their way to the devastated fruit trees.
Piggy was helped to his food and found some by touch. While they ate, Ralph
thought of the afternoon. Well be like we were. We'll wash. Sam gulped
down a mouthful and protested. But we bathe every day. Ralph looked at the
filthy objects before him inside. We ought to comb our hair. Only it's too
long. I've got both socks left in the shelter, said Eric. So we could pull
them over our heads like caps, sort of. We could find some stuff, said
Piggy, and tie your hair back like a girl. No, of course not. Then we must go
as we are, said Ralph, and they won't be any better. Eric made a detaining
gesture. But they'll be painted. You know how it is. The others nodded. They
understood only too well the liberation into savagery that the concealing paint
brought. Well, we won't be painted, said Ralph. Because we aren't savages. Sam
and Eric looked at each other. All the same, Ralph shouted. No paint, he tried
to remember. Smoke, he said. We want smoke. He turned on the twins fiercely.
I said smoke. We've got to have smoke.
There was silence except for the multitudinous murmur of the bees. As
last Piggy spoke kindly. Of course we have, cuz the smoke's a signal, and we
can't be rescued if we don't have smoke.
I knew that, shouted Ralph. He pulled his arm away from Pig. Are you
suggesting? I'm just saying what you always say, said Piggy hastily. I
thought for a moment. I hadn't, said Ralph loudly. I knew it all the time. I hadn't
forgotten. Piggy nodded propitiatingly.
You're chief, Ralph. You remember everything. I hadn't forgotten. Of
course not. The twins were examining Ralph curiously, as though they were
seeing him for the first time. They set off along the beach in
formation. Ralph went first, limping a little, his spear carried over one
shoulder. He saw things partially, through the tremble of the heat haze
over the flashing sands, and his own long hair and injuries. Behind him came the twins,
worried now for a while, but full of unquenchable vitality. They said little,
but trailed the butts of their wooden spears, for Piggy had found that by
looking down and shielding his tired sight from the sun, he could just see
these moving along the sand. He walked between the trailing butts, therefore
the conchk held carefully between his two hands. The boys made a compact
little group that moved over the beach, four plateike shadows dancing and
mingling beneath them. There was no sign left of the storm, and the beach was
swept clean like a blade that has been scoured. The sky and the mountain were
at an immense distance, shimmering in the heat, and the reef was lifted by
mirage, floating in a kind of silver pool halfway up the sky. They passed the place where the
tribe had danced. The charred sticks still lay on the rocks where the rain
had quenched them, but the sand by the water was smooth again. They passed this
in silence. No one doubted that the tribe would be found at the castle rock,
and when they came inside of it, they stopped with one accord. The densest
tangle on the island, a mass of twisted stems, black and green and impenetrable,
lay on their left, and tall grass swayed before them. Now Ralph went forward.
Here was the crushed grass where they had all lane when he had gone to
prospect. There was the neck of land, the ledge skirting the rock. Up there
were the red pinnacles. Sam touched his arm. Smoke. There was a tiny smudge of
smoke wavering into the air on the other side of the rock.
some fire, I don't think. Ralph turned.
What are we hiding for? He stepped through the screen of grass onto the
little open space that led to the narrow neck. You two follow behind. I'll go
first, then Piggy a pace behind me. Keep your spear ready. Piggy peered anxiously
into the luminous veil that hung between him and the world. Is it safe? Ain't
there a cliff? I can hear the sea. You keep right close to me. Ralph moved
forward onto the neck. He kicked a stone, and it bounded into the water.
Then the sea sucked down, revealing a red wedi square 40 ft beneath Ralph's
left arm. Am I safe? Quavered Piggy. I feel awful. High above them from the
pinnacles came a sudden shout and then an imitation war cry that was answered
by a dozen voices from behind the rock.
Give me the conchk and stay still. Halt.
Who goes there? Ralph bent back his head and glimpsed Roger's dark face at the
top. You can see who I am, he shouted.
Stop being silly. He put the conchk to his lips and began to blow. Savages
appeared, painted out of recognition, edging around the ledge toward the neck.
They carried spears and disposed themselves to defend the entrance. Ralph
went on blowing and ignored Piggy's terrors. Roger was shouting, "You mind
out. See?" At length, Ralph took his lips away and paused to get his breath
back. His first words were a gasp, but audible, "Calling an assembly." The
savages guarding the neck muttered among themselves, but made no motion. Ralph
walked forwards a couple of steps. A voice whispered urgently behind him.
Don't leave me, Ralph. You kneel down, said Ralph, sideways. And wait till I
come back. He stood halfway along the neck and gazed at the savages intently.
Freed by the paint, they had tied their hair back and were more comfortable than he
was. Ralph made a resolution to tie his own back afterwards. Indeed, he felt
like telling them to wait and doing it there and then, but that was impossible.
The savages sniggered a bit, and one gestured at Ralph with his spear. High
above, Roger took his hands off the lever and leaned out to see what was
going on. The boys on the neck stood in a pool of their own shadow, diminished
to shaggy heads. Piggy crouched, his back shapeless as a sack. I'm calling an
assembly. Silence. Roger took up a small stone and flung it between the twins,
aiming to miss. They started, and Sam only just kept his footing. Some source
of power began to pulse in Roger's body.
Ralph spoke again loudly. I'm calling an assembly. He ran his eye over them.
Where's Jack? The group of boys stirred and consulted. A painted face spoke with
the voice of Robert. "He's hunting, and he said we weren't to let you in." "I've
come to see about the fire," said Ralph, "and about Piggy's specks." The group in
front of him shifted, and laughter shivered outwards from among them.
Light, excited, laughter that went echoing among the tall rocks. A voice spoke from behind
Ralph. "What do you want?" The twins made a bolt past Ralph and got between
him and the entry. He turned quickly.
Jack, identifiable by personality and red hair, was advancing from the forest.
A hunter crouched on either side. All three were masked in black and green.
Behind them on the grass, the headless and punched body of a SA lay where they
had dropped it. Piggy wailed, "Ralph, don't leave me." With ludicrous care, he
embraced the rock, pressing himself to it above the sucking sea. The sniggering
of the savages became a loud, derisive jer. Jack shouted above the noise. You
go away, Ralph. You keep to your end.
This is my end and my tribe. You leave me alone. The jeering died
away. "You pinched Piggy Specks," said Ralph breathlessly. "You've got to give
them back." "Got to? Who says?" Ralph's temper blazed out. "I say you voted for
me for chief, didn't you hear the conchk? You played a dirty trick. We'd
have given you fire if you'd asked for it." The blood was flowing in his
cheeks, and the bunged up eye throbbed.
You could have had fire whenever you wanted, but you didn't. You came
sneaking up like a thief and stole Piggy's glasses. Say that again. Thief.
Thief. Piggy screamed. Ralph, mind me.
Jack made a rush and stabbed at Ralph's chest with spear. Ralph sensed the
position of the weapon from the glimpse he caught Jack's arm and put the thrust
aside with his own butt. Then he brought the end round and caught Jack a stinger
across the ear. They were chest to chest, breathing fiercely, pushing and
glaring. Who's a thief? You are. Jack wrenched free and swung at Ralph with
his spear. By common consent, they were using the spears as sabers now, no
longer daring the lethal points. The blow struck Ralph's spear and slid down
to fall agonizingly on his fingers. Then they were apart once more, their
positions reversed. Jack toward the castle rock and Ralph on the outside toward the
island. Both boys were breathing very heavily. Come on then. Come on.
Tulently, they squared up to each other, but kept just out of fighting distance.
You come on and see what you get. You come on. Piggy clutching the ground was
trying to attract Ralph's attention.
Ralph moved, bent down, kept a weary eye on Jack. Ralph, remember what we came
for. The fire, my specks. Ralph nodded.
He relaxed his fighting muscles, stood easily, and grounded the butt of his
spear. Jack watched him inscraably through his paint. Ralph glanced up at the
pinnacles, then toward the group of savages.
Listen, we've come to say this. First, you've got to give back Piggy specks. If
he hasn't got them, he can't see. You aren't playing the game. The tribe of
painted savages giggled, and Ralph's mind faltered. He pushed his hair up and
gazed at the green and black mask before him, trying to remember what Jack looked
like. Piggy whispered. "And the fire?"
"Oh, yes, then about the fire. I say this again. I've been saying it ever
since we dropped in." He held out his spear and pointed at the savages. Your
only hope is keeping a signal fire going as long as there's light to see. Then
maybe a ship will notice the smoke and come and rescue us and take us home. But
without that smoke, we've got to wait till some ship comes by accident. We
might wait years till we were old. The shivering, silvery, unreal laughter of
the savages sprayed out and echoed away.
A gust of rage shook Ralph. His voice cracked. Don't you understand? You
painted fools. Sam, Eric, Piggy, and me, we aren't enough. We tried to keep the
fire going, but we couldn't. And then you playing at hunting. He pointed past them to where
the trickle of smoke dispersed in the pearly air. Look at that. Call that a
signal fire. That's a cooking fire. Now you'll eat and there will be no smoke.
Don't you understand? There may be a ship out there. He paused, defeated by
the silence and the painted anonymity of the group guarding the entry. Jack
opened a pink mouth and addressed Sam and Eric who were between him and his
tribe. You two get back. No one answered him. The twins, puzzled, looked at each
other while Piggy, reassured by the sessation of violence, stood up
carefully. Jack glanced back at Ralph and then at the twins. Grab them. The
painted group moved around Sam and Eric nervously and unhandily. Once more the silvery
laughter scattered. Sammon Eric protested out of the heart of
civilization. "Oh, I say honestly, their spears were taken from them. Tie them
up." Ralph cried out hopelessly against the black and green mask. Jack, go on,
tie them. Now the painted group felt the otherness of Sam and Eric, felt the
power in their own hands. They felled the twins clumsily and excitedly. Jack
was inspired. He knew that Ralph would attempt a rescue. He struck in a humming
circle behind him, and Ralph only just parried the blow. Beyond them the tribe
and the twins were a loud and writhing heap. Piggy crouched again. Then the
twins lay, astonished, and the tribe stood around them. Jack turned to Ralph
and spoke between his teeth. See, they do what I want. There was silence again.
The twins lay inexpertly tied up, and the tribe watched Ralph to see what he
would do. He numbered them through his fringe, glimpsed the ineffectual smoke.
His temper broke. He screamed at Jack, "You're a beast and a swine and a
bloody, bloody thief." He charged. Jack, knowing this was the crisis, charged,
too. They met with a jolt and bounced apart. Jack swung with his fist at Ralph
and caught him on the ear. Ralph hit Jack in the stomach and made him grunt.
Then they were facing each other again, panting and furious, but unnerved by each other's
ferocity. They became aware of the noise that was the background to this fight,
the steady shrill cheering of the tribe behind them. Piggy's voice penetrated to
Ralph. Let me speak. He was standing in the dust of the fight, and as the tribe
saw his intention, the shrill cheer changed to a steady booing. Piggy held
up the conchk, and the booing sagged a little, then came up again to strength.
"I got the conchk," he shouted. "I tell you, I got the conchk." Surprisingly,
there was silence now. The tribe were curious to hear what amusing thing he
might have to say. Silence and pause, but in the silence, a curious air noise
close by Ralph's head. He gave it half his attention, and there it was again, a
faint z. Someone was throwing stones.
Roger was dropping them, his one hand still on the lever. Below him, Ralph was
a shock of hair, and Piggy a bag of fat.
I got this to say, "You're acting like a crowd of kids?" The booing rose and died
again as Piggy lifted the white magic shell. "Which is better? To be a pack of
painted Indians like you are, or to be sensible like Ralph is?" A great clamor
arose among the savages. Piggy shouted again. Which is better? To have rules
and agree or to hunt and kill. Again the clamor and again zup. Ralph shouted
against the noise. Which is better, law and rescue or hunting and breaking
things up. Now Jack was yelling too, and Ralph could no longer make himself
heard. Jack had backed right against the tribe, and they were a solid mass of
menace that bristled with spears. The intention of a charge was forming among
them. They were working up to it, and the neck would be swept clear. Ralph
stood facing them a little to one side, his spear ready. By him stood Piggy,
still holding out the talisman, the fragile, shining beauty of the shell.
The storm of sound beat at them, an incantation of hatred. High overhead,
Roger, with a sense of delirious abandonment, leaned all his weight on
the lever. Ralph heard the great rock before he saw it.
He was aware of a jolt in the earth that came to him through the soles of his
feet and the breaking sound of stones at the top of the cliff. Then the monstrous
red thing bounded across the neck and he flung himself flat while the tribe
shrieked. The rock struck Piggy a glancing blow from chin to knee. The
conchk exploded into a thousand white fragments and ceased to exist. Piggy,
saying nothing with no time for even a grunt, traveled through the air sideways
from the rock, turning over as he went.
The rock bounded twice and was lost in the forest. Piggy fell 40 ft and landed
on his back across the square red rock in the sea. His head opened and stuff came out
and turned red. Piggy's arms and legs twitched a bit like a pig's after it has been
killed. Then the sea breathed again in a long slow sigh. The water boiled white
and pink over the rock. And when it went sucking back again, the body of Piggy was gone.
This time the silence was complete.
Ralph's lips formed a word, but no sound came. Suddenly, Jack bounded out from
the tribe and began screaming wildly.
See, see, that's what you'll get. I meant that. There isn't a tribe for you
anymore. The conchk is gone. He ran forward, stooping. I'm chief. Viciously,
with full intention, he hurled his spear at Ralph. The point tore the skin and
flesh over Ralph's ribs, then sheared off and fell in the water. Ralph
stumbled, feeling not pain but panic, and the tribe, screaming now like the
chief, began to advance. Another spear, a bent one that would not fly straight,
went past his face, and one fell from on high where Roger was. The twins lay
hidden behind the tribe, and the anonymous devil's faces swarmed across
the neck. Ralph turned and ran. A great noise as of seagulls rose behind him. He
obeyed an instinct that he did not know he possessed, and swerved over the open
space so that the spears went wide. He saw the headless body of the SA and
jumped in time. Then he was crashing through foliage and small boughs and was hidden by the
forest. The chief stopped by the pig, turned and held up his hands. Back, back
to the fort. Presently the tribe returned noisily to the neck where Roger
joined them. The chief spoke to him angrily. Why aren't you on the
watch? Roger looked at him gravely. I just came down. The hangman's horror
clung round him. The chief said no more to him, but looked down at Sam and Eric.
You got to join the tribe. You let me go and
me. The chief snatched one of the few spears that were left and poked Sam in
the ribs. What do you mean by it, eh?
said the chief fiercely. What do you mean by coming with spears? What do you
mean by not joining my tribe? The proddding became rhythmic. Sam yelled.
That's not the way. Roger edged past the chief, only just avoiding pushing him
with his shoulder. The yelling ceased, and Sam and Eric lay looking up in quiet
terror. Roger advanced upon them as one wielding a nameless
authority. Lord of the